Preliminary Inventory to the Samuel Hirsch Papers WAG.051
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Samuel Hirsch Papers
1952-2004
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Hirsch, Samuel, 1923-2009
WAG.051
47 Linear Feet (47 boxes)
Scope and Contents
Included in the collection are files collected by Hirsch through his involvement with the J.P. Stevens Campaign of the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union, the Committee on National Health Insurance, the Full Employment Action Council, the Citizen Labor Energy Coalition, the New York Labor Religion Coalition and other labor and community organizations. Contained in the files are reports, correspondence, newsletters, press releases, leaflets, minutes, government documents, newspaper clippings. The papers provide extensive documentation of labor and community organizing in the New York area during the 1960s and 1970s.
NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Arrangement
The collection is unprocessed.
Historical/Biographical Note
Samuel Hirsch (1923-2009) life-long labor and community activist, was raised in the East New York section of Brooklyn, New York. While attending Thomas Jefferson High School he joined the left leaning American Students Union. He later joined the Young Communist League and the Communist Party before enlisting in the army in 1942 where he served in the Signal Corps. After the war, he went to work for the Cooks Union, Local 89 where he served as welfare fund administrator for the next twenty years.
From this base, Hirsch maintained an intense level of political and trade union activity, often "loaned" to other unions by Local 89's progressive leadership. His political involvement during the 1950s included the following: civil rights work with the Harlem NAACP and the Civil Rights Congress, union organizing, anti-Korean War activism through Veterans for Peace, and his first arrest during his leaderhip in a protest campaign against police brutality. Although he had long-standing conflicts, Hirsch kept close ties to comrades in the community and in the labor movement. It was not until 1957 that he left the Communist Party. For years the FBI harassed him, trying unsuccessfully to enlist him as an anti-Communist witness.
Hirsch helped in the successful campaign to elect Mark Lane to the New York State Assembly through the East Harlem Reform Democrats. Following this, he organized reform Democratic clubs in mostly minority communities and actively participated in city politics. Through his new position in the 1960s, he worked with the civil rights movement and labor unions, including the United Federation of Teachers and Hospital Workers Local 1199. He also organized support for the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party and participated in the Selma March and in school integration fights in New York City. In 1966, he worked with the American Civil Liberties Union in its unsuccessful effort to defeat a police-led referendum banning a civilian review board.
Between 1967 and 1972, Hirsch joined Frank Schonfeld's reform administration of District Council 9 of the Painters Union, serving as head of the Painters Joint Industry Board. It was in this capacity that he played a major role in two successful legislative campaigns: the passage of OSHA (in 1970) and the ban on lead paint. He was co-founder and treasurer of Citizens to End Lead Poisoning (1968-1973). During the same period, Hirsch enrolled in Empire State Labor College and completed a BA in sociology. After 1973 he directed the New York State Committee for National Health Security. As a free lance "pol", he worked in many election campaigns, including Paul O'Dwyer's campaign for NYC Council President. In 1976, Hirsch worked for six months as a policy analyst for the New York State Assembly Labor Committee under the chairmanship of Sysner.
He was hired as an international representative by the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union for its J. P. Stevens Campaign. He served as a trouble-shooter and represented ACTW in its leadership role in campaigns for full employment and environmental legislation. In 1979-1980, with Father Robert F. Kennedy, Jr. he co-founded the New York Labor/Religion Coalition, which brought together unionists and the religious community around common legislative goals and labor struggles. Hirsch served as the Coalition's chair, and later chair emeritus. Throughout the 1980s he worked as a health-care policy consultant, and worked with Ray Rogers' Corporate Campaign, Inc. on the Farm Labor Organizing Committee and Hormel drives. From 1997 he served on Voices for immigrant Justice, a network of NYC and Long Island Catholic dioceses, and was a member of the NYC Central Labor Council's Immigration Sub-committee.
Samuel Hirsch died in New York City in 2009.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Samuel Hirsch in 2000 and 2004. The accession number associated with these gifts is 1982.008.
Hirsch, Samuel, 1923-2009; Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union; New York Labor Religion Coalition
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to Apartheid South Africa, and the divestment campaign., 1985-1998 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to the New York Labor Religion Coalition and lead poisoning., 1984-1993 (Box 2)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union's national boycott of J.P. Stevens. Arranged alphabetically from Articles to Religious Campaigns., 1977-1980 (Box 3)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to the Citizen/Labor Energy Coalition, which advocated for public control over energy utilities., 1979-1982 (Box 4)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to health care and housing in New York State., 1980-1994 (Box 5)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to the Jobs for All Coalition, welfare reform, and workfare., 1985-1997 (Box 6)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and audio tape reels related to health care reform., 1974-1979 (Box 7)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to the East Harlem Reform Democrats, the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party, urban renewal, and political campaigns., 1960-1978 (Box 8)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to health care, especially St. Lukes/Roosevelt Hospital and HMOs., 1981-1993 (Box 9)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to the New York City Coalition to End Lead Poisoning (NYC CELP) and New Yorkers for Affordable Health Coverage (NYFAHC)., 1980-1998 (Box 10)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to occupational safety and health., 1963-1976 (Box 11)
- Correspondence, reports, publications and clippings related to the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Organization of Retirees (ACTOR), the American Association of Retired Persons (AARP), social security, workers compensation, United Food and Commercial Workers (UFCW) Local P-9's strike and boycott campaign against Hormel, Corporate Campaign, and the United Paperworkers International Union (UPIU) strike and boycott campaign against International Paper Company., 1985-1996 (Box 12)
- Miscellaneous subject files arranged alphabetically from AFL-CIO Legislative Alert to Imports., undated (Box 13)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, photographs, and clippings related to social justice and labor issues in the Philippines, China, El Salvador, Nicaragua, Honduras, Guatemala, Mexico, South Africa, Haiti, and Northern Ireland. There are additional materials related to free trade., 1981-1998 (Box 14)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union's national boycott of J.P. Stevens. Arranged alphabetically by cities in New York, from Albany to Utica; then in the same way for cities outside New York; then for retailers., undated (Box 15)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to anti-sweatshop campaigns, immigration, and health care., 1986-1998 (Box 16)
- Miscellaneous subject files arranged alphabetically from Seniors to Youth Employment. This is followed by correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to a jobs campaign advocating full employment., 1977-1980 (Box 17)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to senior citizens, health care, social security, the American Association of Retired Persons (AARP), and New Yorkers for Accessible Health Coverage (NYFAHC)., 1979-1996 (Box 18)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to health care reform campaigns., 1974-1980 (Box 19)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to the National Labor Religion Coalition, primarily in New York State., 1980-1987 (Box 20)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to labor unions, factory closings, unemployment, workmen's compensation, and health care., 1980-2001 (Box 21)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to the campaign for full employment., 1975-1979 (Box 22)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to the Joint Industry Board of the Painting and Decorating Industry, the Building and Construction Trades Council, apprenticeship and training programs in the construction industry, District No. 9 of the Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators, and Paperhangers of America, and urban renewal. Includes item: "McGee, Willie: Flyer for Rally, NYC (with Josephine Baker, Paul Robeson, Vito Marcantonio, et al), Mar 19, 1951, 1951-1973 (Box 23)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to issues relevant to senior citizens, including, health care, social security, finance, and recreation., 1974-1983 (Box 24)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to the American Federation of Musicians (especially local 802), union reform, union busting, the campaign for full employment, work sharing, and various labor struggles that Hirsch was part of., 1980-1992 (Box 25)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to the National Labor/Religion Coalition, primarily in New York City, but also elsewhere in New York and New Jersey., 1986-2001 (Box 26)
- Health care subject files arranged alphabetically from Cornell-Health to NYSCNHS-Tristate-Minutes., 1974-1980 (Box 27)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to labor struggles involving the following unions, among others: United Farmworkers of America (UFWA); the locals 111, 237, 282, 680, 819, 966, and the leadership of the International Brotherhood of Teamsters (IBT); Local 100 of the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE); the United Needletrade and Industrial Employees Union (UNITE); Locals 32B-32J, 74, 144, 365, and 925 of the Service Employees International Union (SEIU); Local 919 of the United Paperworkers International Union (UPIU); Local 3 of the Newspaper Guild; the Chinese Staff and Workers Association; District 65 and Locals 2110 and 2325 of the United Auto Workers (UAW); Locals 306 and B571 of the International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees (IATSE); District 1199 of the Hospital & Health Care Employees Union; the Union for the Performing Arts; United University Professionals (UUP); United Rubber Workers Union; Local 404 of the United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America (UE); DC 1707 and Local 1000 of the American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME); the Farm Labor Organizing Committee (FLOC); the United Steelworkers of America; the Committee of Interns and Residents (CIR); Local 342 of the United Food and Commercial Workers International Union (UFCW); Locals 100, 234, and 1400 of the Transit Workers Union (TWU); and Local 16 of the National Association of Broadcast Employees and Technicians (NABET)., 1981-1998 (Box 28)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to the National Labor/Religion Coalition in New York State., 1988-2002 (Box 29)
- Miscellaneous subject files arranged alphabetically from INFACT (Infant Formula Action Coalition) to SALT., undated (Box 30)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to education, 9/11 memorial, the "Killer Coke" campaign, prison reform, police brutality and racial profiling, the Third World, New York State Labor Religion Coalition, labor unions (especially union reform), the Hale House charity, and leftist political parties., 1987-2002 (Box 31)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to the campaign for universal health care. There is also miscellaneous correspondence to and from the White House, U.S. Congress, the New York State legislature, and the New York City municipal government., 1975-1994 (Box 32)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to child labor, rent control, prison reform, sweatshops, New York Labor Religion Coalition, health care, labor unions, senior citizens, Transport Workers Union (TWU) Local 100, City University of New York (CUNY), State University of New York (SUNY), election reform, the death penalty, and oil drilling in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge., 1987-2004 (Box 33)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to the Trade Union Health Education Project at the New York State School of Industrial & Labor Relations, Cornell University. There is also material on the health care system in New York City., 1969-1975 (Box 34)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to the campaign for national health insurance and the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union's national boycott of J.P. Stevens. Also includes a film reel of a television program on the subject of national health insurance [REMOVED]., 1973-1979 (Box 35)
- Correspondence, reports, publications and clippings related to lead poisoning., 1956-1981 (Box 36)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to New Yorkers for Accessible Health Coverage (NYFAHC) and the New York City Committee to End Lead Poisoning (NYC CELP)., 1998-2003 (Box 37)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to health care., 1980-1988 (Box 38)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, posters, and clippings related to the Full Employment Action Council (FEAC), voter registration, occupational safety and health, and work sharing., 1972-1985 (Box 39)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to health care reform., 1974-1999 (Box 40)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to health care reform and the Committee to End Lead Poisoning (CELP)., 1976-2004 (Box 41)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, clippings, and audiotapes related to the Community Council of Greater New York, the campaign for full employment, and unemployment., 1977-1983 (Box 42)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to religious (primarily Catholic and Jewish) social justice organizations, the Christian right, and the New York City Labor Religion Coalition., 1982-1998 (Box 43)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to immigration reform, hate crimes, immigrant rights, unemployment, labor organizing among immigrants, and the Greater New York Labor Religion Coalition., 1982-2004 (Box 44)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to voter registration, Paul O'Dwyer's 1976 US Senate bid, INFACT (Infant Formula Action Coalition), the campaign for full employment, CLEC (Citizen/Labor Energy Coalition), urban renewal in New York City, housing in New York City, occupational safety and health, and workers compensation., 1960-1982 (Box 45)
- Correspondence, reports, and publications related to the National Labor Religion Coalition, especially the New York branch., 1981-1990 (Box 46)
- Correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings related to health care reform., 1974-1979 (Box 47)
- Committee for National Health, "Paid in Full" (Reel 48)
- Photograph: Labor memorial, 1993 (Box Shared Tamiment 018, Folder 2)